Finding Aid for J. Philip Wernette Papers, 1915-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
J. Philip Wernette Papers 1915-1987
Wernette, J. Philip (John Philip), 1903-1988.
90163 Aa 2
President of the University of New Mexico, later professor of business administration at the University of Michigan. Biographical and personal materials; correspondence, 1929-1987; topical files, 1942-1985; speeches and writings, 1932-1980; career files detailing various university and consulting work, notably his interest in executive training.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
12 linear feet
The collection was donated by Mrs. Eleanor DeCourcy Wernette (Donor No. 7782 ) in March 1990.
The collection is open to research.
John Philip Wernette was born October 29, 1903 in Imlay City, Michigan. He received his A.B. from the University of California at Berkeley in 1924, a master's degree from the University of Southern California in 1926, a second master's degree from Harvard University in 1929, and a Ph.D. from the Department of Economics at Harvard in 1932. He and Eleanor DeCourcy were married in 1940, and had two children, John and Elizabeth.
Professor Wernette served on the Harvard faculty from 1927 to 1945, first in the Economics Department and after 1935 in the Graduate School of Business Administration. In 1945 he was named president of the University of New Mexico, and remained there until 1948, when he was dismissed by the Board of Regents due to a disagreement over the appointment of two faculty members whom Professor Wernette felt to be unqualified. In 1948 he came to the University of Michigan, where he was a professor at the Graduate School of Business Administration for 26 years. He founded the Michigan Business Review in 1949 and served as its editor until his retirement. He received the University of Michigan Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award in 1965. After his retirement in 1974, he was Professor Emeritus of Business Administration and Editor Emeritus of the Michigan Business Review.
Professor Wernette's special interest in the economic relationship between government and business was reflected in his varied activities outside the academic sphere. He acted as an economic adviser to foreign governments, to the U.S. government, and to various businesses. In 1929, he served on a fiscal advisory commission to the Republic of Colombia, acting as an expert on taxation. In 1931, he was a member of the Kemmerer Commission, which provided fiscal advice to the Republic of Peru. During 1942 and 1943, he served on the Procurement Policy Board and was war goods price coordinator for the Office of Price Administration. In 1955, he acted as a State Department lecturer in South America.
Professor Wernette consistently maintained an optimistic outlook on the future of the economy, and from the early 1950s until his retirement, he shared this outlook with the business community through extensive travel and speeches. Until the early 1980s, he was also involved in several executive training programs (in particular, the University of Michigan's Executive Development Program). He also had a long-term relationship with the Ohio Citizens Trust Company of Toledo, Ohio, serving on the Board of Directors and as an economic consultant. Professor Wernette was the author of eight books and many articles. He died on August 12, 1988.
The collection has been arranged into six series: Biographical/Personal, Correspondence, Topical Files, Speeches and Writings, Career Materials, 1926-1948 and Career Materials, 1948 to 1985. Biographical and autobiographical materials and photographs have been placed at the beginning of the collection. In general, much of the material relates to Professor Wernette's writings and to his relationship with the business community. Little material about his teaching career at the University of Michigan or about the Michigan Business Review is included.
Subjects:
Colombia.; Executives--Training of.; Ohio Citizens Trust Company.; University of New Mexico. President.; Peru.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Wernette, J. Philip (John Philip), 1903-1988.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
United States. Office of Price Administration.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Wernette, J. Philip (John Philip), 1903-1988.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical material (Box 1)
  - Photographs: portraits, and photographs of Wernette as part of official grouping (Box 1)
  - Junior High yearbook, Grand Rapids 1915 (Box 1)
  - High School yearbook, Grand Rapids 1917 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1929-1987
  The Correspondence series was maintained in its original alphabetical order. The bulk of the materials date from the 1950s through the early 1980s. It includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence, largely concerned with Professor Wernette's economic theories. Some personal correspondence is included, and further correspondence may be found within the Topical Files and the Career Materials series.
  - unidentified 1957-1985 (Box 1)
  - A (Box 1)
  - B (Box 1)
  - Bond, Floyd (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - D (Box 1)
  - E (Box 1)
  - F (Box 1)
  - G (Box 1)
  - Goodwin, E.S.L., 4 folders (Box 1)
  - General Motors Truck and Coach Division (Box 1)
  - H (Box 1)
  - I (Box 1)
  - J (Box 1)
  - K (Box 1)
  - Kerby, Bill (Box 1)
  - Kerby, Bill (cont.) (Box 2)
  - L (Box 2)
  - Lane, William-General Motors (Box 2)
  - M (Box 2)
  - Macmillan Publishing, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Insurance (Box 2)
  - N (Box 2)
  - National Association of Business Economists (Box 2)
  - O (Box 2)
  - P (Box 2)
  - Publishers (Box 2)
  - R (Box 2)
  - S (Box 2)
  - State Department, South America 1955 (Box 2)
  - T (Box 2)
  - U (Box 2)
  - V (Box 2)
  - W (Box 2)
  - Y (Box 2)
  - Z (Box 2)
- Topical Files 1942-1985
  The Topical Files have been arranged alphabetically, and vary widely. Some reflect particular activities or organizations, while others are reference files for various writings. When possible, the folders have been given rough dates. Included are eight folders of miscellaneous material which was received unfoldered and unsorted.
  - Agrocracy, representation 1956-1964 (Box 2)
  - Basing-point material 1942-1966 (Box 2)
  - Corrections 1950-1959 (Box 2)
  - Environment/pollution 1956-1973 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of teaching 1944, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Financing Full Employment 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - Farrar and Rinehart 1944 (Box 2)
  - Future of American Prosperity reviews 1955 (Box 2)
  - Futurism (Box 3)
  - General Motors (Box 3)
  - General Motors 1954-1975 (Box 3)
  - General Motors 1976-1980 (Box 3)
  - Gilder, George 1981 (Box 3)
  - Growth and Prosperity reviews (Box 3)
  - LEAD Program 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Master sheets (Box 3)
  - McCracken, Paul 1970-1985 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Business Review (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous materials, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - National Economic Planning 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Nature and Extent of Competition 1961 (Box 3)
  - Press releases and clippings 1955-1981 (Box 3)
  - Soviet Union 1951-1972 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan
    - Research Club 1956-1982 (Box 4)
    - School of Business Administration
      - Syllabi 1978-1983 (Box 4)
      - Class readings 1949-1973 (Box 4)
    - Senate Advisory Committee 1959-1960 (Box 4)
  - Verses (Box 4)
- Speeches and Writings 1932-1980
  The Speeches and Writings is the largest series (4 linear ft.), and consists of two subseries, Manuscript Materials and Published Materials. The manuscript materials have been arranged alphabetically by the title of the article or speech, and dated when possible. The published materials include copies of five of Professor Wernette's eight books, plus two linear feet of journals and reprints which have not been arranged.
  - Manuscript Materials
    - American Political Economy (law school outlines) (Box 4)
    - Appraisal of Full-Employment Budget 1972 (Box 4)
    - Book review of Janeway's Economics of Crisis 1968 (Box 4)
    - Book review: two books about banks and bankers 1975 (Box 4)
    - Boston Sunday Post articles 1937-1939 (Box 4)
    - Building a Boring Banquet 1968 (Box 4)
    - Building a Greater America (Box 4)
    - Business Can Influence Government 1968 (Box 4)
    - A Business Reading List (Box 4)
    - Canadian Prosperity 1967 (Box 4)
    - The Case Method 1963 (Box 4)
    - Cheer Up, America! (Box 4)
    - Collegiate Education for Business 1960 (Box 4)
    - Comments on the Economic Reports (Box 4)
    - Commercial and Financial Chronicle articles 1965 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Economic Club 1969, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Detroit News articles 1956-1967 (Box 4)
    - Diagram of American Economic System (Box 4)
    - Economic Theory 1942 (Box 4)
    - England and the English People 1933 (Box 4)
    - English Banking 1933 (Box 4)
    - Executive Philosophy and Practice 1966 (Box 4)
    - Factors in the Business Outlook 1969 (Box 4)
    - The Future of the Automobile (Box 4)
    - General Motors: The Past Half Century and the Next Half Century 1958 (Box 4)
    - GMC: Outlook for the Dynamic American Economy (Box 4)
    - GNP and GNE 1974 (Box 4)
    - The Gold Problem (Box 4)
    - The Good Life Ahead in Ann Arbor (Box 4)
    - Holmes and Watson Were Wrong 1969 (Box 5)
    - How Long the Business Slump? (Box 5)
    - How Much Government? 1965 (Box 5)
    - Image of the Businessman 1962 (Box 5)
    - The Impact of Communism 1971 (Box 5)
    - The Impact of Fiscal Policy 1971 (Box 5)
    - Impressions of Soviet Russia 1933 (Box 5)
    - Inflation: Fact and Fancy 1965 (Box 5)
    - Is America Going Bankrupt? 1953 (Box 5)
    - Is the Surtax Necessary? (Box 5)
    - Los Angeles Times articles 1967-1969 (Box 5)
    - Martin and the "Fed" 1966 (Box 5)
    - Mathematics for Business Training (Box 5)
    - Meeting Society's Challenges to Businesses 1971 (Box 5)
    - Meeting the Attacks on Free Enterprise (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Writings (Box 5)
    - Money Manager Martin 1965 (Box 5)
    - Monopolistic Competition, Chamberlin 1937 (Box 5)
    - The Need for Accurate Measurement of the Impact of the Budget on the Economy (Box 5)
    - A New Curriculum for Business Administration 1967 (Box 5)
    - 1981 A Year of Transition (Box 5)
    - Ohio Citizens Trust Company, Tempo newsletter column 1961-1976 (Box 5)
    - On Maximizing Profits 1967 (Box 5)
    - The Outlook for American Business (Box 5)
    - The Outlook for the American Economy (Box 5)
    - The Outlook for the American Economy in the Seventies (Box 5)
    - The Perils and Promise of Prosperity 1970 (Box 5)
    - Perspective on Environmental Problems 1975 (Box 5)
    - The President 1966 (Box 5)
    - Progress of the Trillion Dollar Economy 1970 (Box 5)
    - The Promise of Prosperity (Box 5)
    - Proper Role of Government (Box 5)
    - Report from Iron Mountain (Box 5)
    - Shorter Work Week (Box 5)
    - Soaring Sixties and Surging Seventies 1969 (Box 5)
    - The Social Responsibilities of Business 1971 (Box 5)
    - Speech Titles (Box 5)
    - Spirit of Enterprise 1967 (Box 5)
    - Summaries of Talks 1950-1968 (Box 5)
    - Swigart 1979-1980 (Box 5)
    - Talks in El Salvador 1954 (Box 5)
    - Talks in South America 1955 (Box 5)
    - Time Deposits 1963 (Box 5)
    - A Time for Confidence 1968 (Box 5)
    - The Trillion Dollar Economy 1967 (Box 5)
    - TV program outline (University of Michigan), The American Economic System 1954 (Box 6)
    - TV program script, The Ten Million Dollar Bill 1965 (Box 6)
    - TV/Radio program proposal, Building a Greater America (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Press Club speech 1969 (Box 6)
    - What Do Managers Do? (Box 6)
    - What Does Pound Devaluation Mean to Us? 1966 (Box 6)
    - What's Ahead for American Business 1958 (Box 6)
    - What is Economics? (Box 6)
    - What's True of America is True of General Motors (Box 6)
    - Who Voted for Goldwater? 1964 (Box 6)
  - Published Materials
    - Money, Business and Prices 1933 (Box 6)
    - The Control of Business Cycles 1940 (Box 6)
    - Financing Full Employment 1945 (Box 6)
    - The Future of American Prosperity 1955 (Box 6)
    - Growth and Prosperity Without Inflation 1961 (Box 6)
    - Government and Business 1964 (Box 6)
    - Executive Philosophy and Practice (editor) 1965 (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook: "Articles By Wernette" (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous journals and reprints 1932-1979, 0.5 linear feet (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous journals and reprints 1932-1979 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous journals and reprints 1932-1979, 0.5 linear feet (Box 8)
- Career Materials 1926-1948
  The Career Materials, 1926-1948 are arranged chronologically, and include writings, teaching materials, correspondence and reports of the financial advisory commissions to Colombia and Peru. In some cases these financial reports have been retained in both English and Spanish, when one version included material not found in the other. Also of interest is correspondence relating to the controversy over the appointment of two faculty members at the University of New Mexico, which resulted in the dismissal of Dr. Wernette by the Board of Regents.
  - University of Southern California, M.A. thesis, "The Relation of Government to Industry" 1926 (Box 8)
  - Harvard University, class notes, "Public Finance" 1927-1928 (Box 8)
  - Republic of Columbia
    - Fiscal advisory commission reports 1929 (Box 8)
      (bound, in English)
    - Fiscal advisory commission reports 1929, 7 folders (Box 8)
      (in Spanish)
    - Financial reorganization publications 1929 (Box 8)
  - Republic of Peru (Box 9)
    - Kemmerer Commission reports 1931, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Kemmerer Commission reports 1931, 19 pamphlets (Box 9)
      (in English and Spanish)
    - Kemmerer Commission scrapbook 1931 (Box 9)
  - Harvard University
    - Ph.D. thesis, "Branch Banking in California" 1932 (Box 9)
    - Problems in Economic Theory 1936 (draft for 1939 book) (Box 9)
    - Economic Problems of National Defense
      - 1940-1941 (Box 9)
      - 1941-1942, 2 volumes (Box 9)
  - Office of Price Administration 1942-1943 (Box 10)
  - University of New Mexico 1946-1948
    - General, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Wernette inauguration 1946 (Box 10)
    - Bulletin 1947 (Box 10)
    - Clippings (Box 10)
    - Allen and Kleven material (re: controversy over appointment of faculty) (Box 10)
- Career Materials 1949-1985
  The Career Materials, 1949-1985 series is composed of two subseries, Executive Training Files and Ohio Citizens Trust Company. The executive training materials include correspondence, agendas and topics covered. Of particular interest is material relating to the University of Michigan's Executive Development Program from 1972 to 1982. The Ohio Citizens Trust Company materials document Wernette's twenty-six year relationship with the company, and include files of his monthly reports to the directors dating from 1957 to 1983, plus files of yearly economic forecast booklets dating from 1961 to 1982.
  - Executive Training Files
    - Advanced Bank Management Seminar 1961 (Box 10)
    - American Electric Power
      - 1976 (Box 10)
      - 1977 (Box 10)
      - 1978 (Box 10)
      - 1979
        - General (Box 10)
        - Topic I: The Political Economy of the Private Enterprise System (Box 10)
        - Topic II: American Government: Nature, Growth and Functioning (Box 10)
        - Topic III: The American Economic System: Growth and Functioning (Box 10)
        - Topic IV: Stable Prosperity: Monetary and Fiscal Policies (Box 10)
        - Topic V: Inflation (Box 10)
        - Topic VI: The Outlook for the Dynamic American Economy (Box 10)
      - 1980 (Box 10)
      - 1981 (Box 10)
    - Pacific Coast Banking School
      - 1951
        - General (Box 10)
        - Lecture notes (Box 10)
      - 1961
        - General (Box 10)
        - Topics (Box 10)
    - Executive Administration (Box 10)
    - Executive Development Program, University of Michigan
      - 1954 (Box 10)
      - 1972 (Box 10)
      - 1974 (Box 10)
      - 1975 (Box 11)
      - 1976
        - General (Box 11)
        - I. The Political Economy of the Private Enterprise System (Box 11)
        - II. American Government: Growth and Functioning (Box 11)
        - III. Stable Economic Growth (Box 11)
        - IV. The Outlook for the Dynamic American Economy (Box 11)
      - 1977 (Box 11)
      - 1978 (Box 11)
      - 1979 (Box 11)
    - New Frontiers, University of Michigan 1981 (Box 11)
    - Executive Academy, University of Michigan
      - 1979-1981 (Box 11)
      - 1982 (Box 11)
      - Notes (Box 11)
  - Ohio Citizens Trust Company
    - General 1957-1981 (Box 11)
    - Speeches 1957-1963 (Box 11)
    - Business outlook 1978-1983 (Box 11)
    - Trust Committee
      - General 1971-1977 (Box 11)
      - Reports to 1976-1983 (Box 11)
    - Monthly reports to directors
      - 1957-1959 (Box 11)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 11)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 11)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 11)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 12)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 12)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 12)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 12)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 12)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 12)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 12)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 12)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 12)
    - Economic forecast booklets
      - 1958 (Box 12)
      - 1961-1983, 23 folders (Box 12)
    - Annual reports
      - 1956 (Box 12)
      - 1957 (Box 12)
      - 1959 (Box 12)
      - 1961 (Box 12)
      - 1962 (Box 12)
      - 1963 (Box 12)
      - 1964 (Box 12)
      - 1965 (Box 12)
      - 1969 (Box 12)
      - 1972 (Box 12)
      - 1973 (Box 12)
      - 1974 (Box 12)
      - 1975 (Box 12)
      - 1976 (Box 12)
      - 1977 (Box 12)
      - 1978 (Box 12)
      - 1979 (Box 12)
      - 1980 (Box 12)
      - 1981 (Box 12)